-The neat thing about working in ML
is, every few years,
somebody invents something crazy
that makes you
totally reconsider what's possible,
like models that can play Go
or generate hyper-realistic faces.
Today, the mind-blowing discovery
rocking everyone's world
is a type of neural network
called a transformer.
Transformers are models that can
translate text, write poems and op-eds,
and generate computer code.
These will used in biology
to solve the protein folding problem.
Transformers are like
a magical machine learning hammer
that used to make every problem into a nail.
If you've heard of the trendy new ML models,
BERT or GPT-3 or T-5,
all of these models
are based on transformers.
If you want to stay hip in machine learning,
especially in natural language processing,
you must know about the transformer.
In this video,
I'll tell you about what transformers are,
how they work
and why they've been so impactful.
Let's get to it.
So what is a transformer?
It's a type of neural network architecture.
To recap, neural networks
are a very effective type of model
for analyzing complicated data types
like images, videos, audio and text.
Different neural networks
are optimized for different data types.
Like, if you're analyzing images,
you typically use
a convolutional neural network
which is designed to vaguely mimic
the way the human brain processes vision.
Since around 2012,
neural networks have been really good
at solving vision tasks
like identifying objects in photos.
But, for a long time,
there wasn't a comparably good
option for analyzing language,
whether for translation
or text summarization or text generation.
This is a problem because language
is the main way humans communicate.
Until transformers came around, the way
we use deep learning to understand text
was with a type of model called
a recurrent neural network, or an RNN,
that looks something like this.
Say you wanted to translate
a sentence from English to French.
An RNN would take as input
an English sentence
and process the words one at a time
and then sequentially
spit out their French counterparts.
The key word here is "sequential."
In language, the order of words matters,
and you can't just shuffle them around.
For example, the sentence
"Jane went looking for trouble"
means something very different than
"Trouble went looking for Jane."
Any model dealing with language
has to capture word order
and recurrent neural networks do this
by looking at one word
at a time sequentially.
But RNNs had a lot of problems.
First, they never really did  well
at handling large sequences of text
like long paragraphs or essays.
By time the end of a paragraph is analyzed,
they'd forget the beginning of it.
And, even worse,
RNNs were pretty hard to train.
Because they process words sequentially,
they couldn't parallelize well,
meaning you couldn't speed them up
by throwing lots of GPUs at them.
With a model that's slow to train,
you can't train it on that much data.
This is where
the transformer changed everything.
They were a model developed in 2017
by Google researchers
and the University of Toronto.
They were initially designed for translation,
but unlike RNNs,
you could really efficiently
parallelize transformers.
That meant, with the right hardware,
you can train really big models.
How big?
Really big.
Remember GPT-3 that model that writes
poetry and code and has conversations?
That was trained
on almost 45 terabytes of text data,
including like almost the entire public web.
If you remember anything
about transformers, let it be this:
combine a model
that scales really well with a huge dataset,
the results will probably blow your mind.
How do these things actually work?
Based on the diagram,
it should be pretty clear!
Or maybe not.
Actually, it's simpler than you'd think.
There are 3 main innovations
making this model work so well:
Positional encodings, and attention,
and specifically a type
of attention called self-attention.
Let's talk about the first one:
positional encodings.
Say we're translating text
from English to French.
Positional encodings is that,
instead of looking at words sequentially,
you take each word
and before feeding it to a neural network,
you slap a number on it--
1, 2, 3, depending on what number
the word is in the sentence.
In other words, store information
about word order in the data
rather than in the structure of the network.
Then, as you train the network on text data,
it learns how to interpret
those positional encodings.
In this way, the neural network learns
the importance of word order from the data.
This is a high-level understanding
of positional encodings,
but it's an innovation that really helped
make transformers easier to train than RNNs.
The next innovation in this paper
is a concept called attention,
which you see used often in ML these days.
In fact, the title
of the original transformer paper
is "Attention Is All You Need."
"The agreement on the European Economic Area
was signed in August 1992."
Did you know that?
That's the example sentence
in the original paper,
and remember the original transformer
was designed for translation.
Now, imagine trying
to translate that sentence to French.
One bad way to translate text
is to try to translate each word one for one.
In French, some words are flipped
like, in the French translation,
"European" comes before "economic."
Plus, French is a language
with gendered agreement between words.
So the word "européenne"
needs to be in the feminine form
to match with "la zone."
The attention mechanism
is a neural network structure
allows a text model to look
at every single word in the original sentence
when making a decision about
translating a word in the output sentence.
Here's a nice visualization from that paper
that shows what words in
the input sentence the model is attending to
when it makes predictions
about a word for the output sentence.
So, when the model
outputs the word "européenne,"
it's looking at the input words
"European" and "economic,"
you can think of this diagram
as a sort of heat map for attention
and how does the model know
which words it should be attending to?
It's something
that's learned over time from data.
By seeing many examples
of French and English sentence pairs,
the model learns about gender, word order,
and plurality, and all the grammatical stuff.
We talked about
two key transformer innovations,
positional encoding and attention,
but actually attention
had been invented before this paper.
The real innovation in transformers
was something called self-attention.
A twist on traditional attention.
The type of attention we talked about
has to do with aligning words in languages,
really important for translation,
but what if you're just trying to understand
the underlying meaning in language
so that you can build a network
that can do any number of language tasks.
What's incredible
about neural networks like transformers
is that, as they analyze tons of text data,
they begin to build up
this internal representation
or understanding of language automatically.
They may learn, for example,
that the words "programmer,"
"software engineer," and "software developer"
are all synonymous.
They may also naturally learn the rules
of grammar, gender and tense, and so on.
The better the internal
representation of language that's learned,
the better it will be at any language task.
It turns out
attention can be an effective way
to get a neural network
to understand language
if it's turned on the input text itself.
Let me give you an example.
Take these two sentences:
"Server, can I have the check?"
versus
"Looks like I just crashed the server."
The word "server" here
means two very different things.
I know that because I'm looking
at the context of the surrounding words.
Self-attention allows a neural network
to understand a word
in the context of the words around it.
When a model processes
"server" in the first sentence,
it might be attending to the word "check"
which helps it disambiguate
from a human server versus a metal one.
In the second sentence,
the model may attend to the word "crashed"
to determine this server is a machine.
Self-attention
can also help disambiguate words,
recognize parts of speech,
and even identify word tense.
This, in a nutshell,
is the value of self-attention.
So, to summarize, transformers boil down to:
positional encodings,
attention, and self-attention.
Of course,
this is a 10,000-foot look at transformers.
But how are they actually useful?
One of the most popular
transformer-based models is called BERT,
which was invented just around
the time that I joined Google in 2018.
BERT was trained on a massive text corpus
and has become
this sort of general pocket knife for NLP
that can be adapted
to a bunch of different tasks
like text summarization, question answering,
classification,
and finding similar sentences.
It's used in Google Search
to help understand search queries,
and it powers
a lot of Google Cloud's NLP tools,
like Google Cloud AutoML Natural Language.
BERT also proved that you could
build very good models on unlabeled data,
like text scraped from Wikipedia or Reddit.
This is called semi-supervised learning,
a big trend in machine learning now.
GETTING STARTED WITH TRANSFORMERS
So, if I've sold you
on how cool transformers are,
you may want to use them in your app.
No problem.
Tensorflow Hub is a great place to grab
pre-trained transformer models like BERT.
Download them for free in multiple languages
and drop them straight into your app.
You can also check out
the popular Transformers Python Library
built by Hugging Face,
a favorite way of the community
to train and use transformer models.
For more transformer tips,
check out my blog post link below,
and thanks for watching!
BUILD ANYTHING WITH GOOGLE.
LINKS IN THE DESCRIPTION BELOW